[Music]
today you can get your dna sequence the
letters of your entire genetic code
spelled out for like a thousand bucks a
bargain compared to the 100 million or
so it cost 20 years ago and for around a
hundred dollars you can get partial dna
sequencing it's only a click away direct
to consumer genetic testing like 23andme
for ancestry health love you name it
unfortunately many tests currently
offered have not been appropriately
validated and consequently the consumer
may be paying for something that's
ultimately useless or just fled out
wrong
there's an increasing demand from the
public for direct-to-consumer genetic
tests but when put to the test
researchers found an alarmingly high
false positive rate meaning the analysis
said you had some high-risk gene but it
simply wasn't true
and this happened 40 percent of the time
like they said you had the angelina
jolie brocco breast cancer genes but it
wasn't true
and in addition to the 40 false positive
rate some variants they did identify
correctly were misclassified as being
high risk when in actuality they weren't
high risk at all
you can see how it's in these companies
best interest to give you scary outlier
results so you'll think the money was
worth it and pay for additional testing
but both false positive results and
misclassification of variance can result
in
significant implications for an
individual including unnecessary stress
and even unnecessary medical procedures
i mean what if you got a preventive
double mastectomy because you falsely
thought you were at high risk when you
didn't even have the brac mutations
yes these genome-wide association
studies have now successfully identified
thousands of common genetic variants
that influence the risk of complex
diseases as i've talked about in my
video on personalized nutrition
but nevertheless the discovered gene
variants do not markedly expand our
predictive ability compare with what can
be achieved by using only information
from long known traditional risk factors
take
type 2 diabetes for example we've
identified about 50 genes that are
linked to increased diabetes risk but
even if you put them all together
obese persons with the lowest genetic
risk for diabetes were nearly five times
more likely to develop disease than
normal weight persons with the highest
genetic risk in other words
this would send out the wrong message to
someone who was obese giving them a
false sense of security
knowledge about type 2 diabetes genetic
susceptibility based on what we know so
far has
no implications for decisions about who
should be targeted for intensive
lifestyle interventions
everyone with excessive body fat
regardless of genetics needs to slim
down to reduce the risk of diabetes
what about this famous study that
purported to show that personally
tailored dietary interventions could
improve blood sugar responses to the
extent that some commentators said it
raised questions about the usefulness of
universal dietary recommendations period
but if you actually read the study it
turns out the results do not demonstrate
high interpersonal variation and
relative blood sugar responses do not
show that their model is superior to
current methods of detecting high blood
sugars and do not show that personalized
nutrition advice is superior to standard
dietary advice to manage high blood
sugar responses after meals
but hey what about personalized genetic
risk counseling just to at least
motivate diabetes prevention
in a somewhat forlorn bid to regain
credibility knowledge of individual
genetic risk profiles has been touted as
effective in motivating people to commit
more strenuously to relevant disease
prevention efforts
here again however available evidence
does not support the claims and indeed
it did not seem to help those at risk
for diabetes randomized people to get
genetic tests worth hundreds or
thousands of dollars profiling their
subtle differences in risk for up to 40
different diseases in this case it was
navigenex who described their goal as
empowering people with personal genetic
insights to help motivate them to
improve their health yet
it didn't work
no measurable changes in diet and
lifestyle even in the short term
randomized people to personalize
nutrition insights like determining who
might genetically benefit particularly
well from eating more greens or or
eating to lower their cholesterol yet
there was no significant changes in diet
at month six compared to those who
didn't get that personalized info or
even a month three so it's no surprise
there weren't any differences in weight
or belly fat cholesterol or any of the
other biomarkers
put all the studies together and what do
we find no significant benefits for
telling smokers who's at particular risk
for lung cancer for instance or who
needs to eat particularly healthy or
move especially more
bottom line is that expectations that
communicating dna-based risk estimates
changes behavior is not supported by
existing evidence yet that was the
stated reason for the big presidential
push for precision medicine to empower
individuals to take a more active role
in their own health
it's no surprise that the theme of
personal empowerment is invoked it's
great for marketing but it's not
particularly empowering in fact if
anything it leaves patients even more
reliant on authority and it's not even
very personal since the genetic
contributions we know of are so small
compared to how we actually live our
lives
why then is patient empowerment
emphasized as its cardinal virtue
because it exploits the appeal to
generate political and public support
for an increasingly industrialized
medical industrial scientific complex
which moves literally trillions of
dollars around the globe
this isn't some grand conspiracy theory
it's just the way the system works
healthy living directly threatens many
powerful corporations i mean eat less
sugar eat less meat
and healthier populations do nothing but
lower the demand for doctors and drugs
seemingly willfully blind to this
evidence the united states continues to
overwhelmingly spend its health dollars
on clinical care cleaning up our
lifestyle-induced messes so it's not
surprising that we far outspend other
countries while at the same time have
worse outcomes
while major new taxpayer gifts were
being promised to high-tech medicine the
united states had already sunk to the
bottom of the list of comparable
countries in terms of disease experience
and life expectancy
overrated precision medicine promises
may be serving vested interest
justifying the exorbitant health care
expenditures in our finance based
medicine
but in many ways the american health
care system is the most advanced in the
world yet all our whiz-bang technology
cannot fix
what ails us
let's start with the basics eat your
broccoli take the stairs and don't worry
about whether you have a 5.6 or 7.7
lifetime risk for grave disease because
either way a sensible lifestyle
is the healthiest choice
[Music]
so
you